Five years ago, I was a Ph.D. student
قبل خمس سنوات، كنت طالب دكتوراه
living two lives.
أعيش حياتين.
In one, I used NASA supercomputers
أحدها، هي استخدامي للحواسيب الخارقة لوكالة ناسا
to design next-generation spacecraft,
لتصميم الجيل القادم من المركبات الفضائية،
and in the other I was a data scientist
وفي الثانية كنت عالم البيانات
looking for potential smugglers
أبحث عن المهربين المحتملين
of sensitive nuclear technologies.
للتقنيات النووية الحساسة.
As a data scientist, I did a lot of analyses,
وكعالم بيانات، قمت بالكثير من التحليلات،
mostly of facilities,
بشكل رئيسي عن ،
industrial facilities around the world.
الوسائل الصناعية في العالم.
And I was always looking for a better canvas
وكنت دائماً أتطلع لأفضل وسيلة
to tie these all together.
لربطها مع بعضها.
And one day, I was thinking about how
وفي أحد الأيام، كنت أفكر بأن
all data has a location,
لكل من البيانات موقع محدد،
and I realized that the answer
وأدركت أن الإجابة
had been staring me in the face.
تحدق بي.
Although I was a satellite engineer,
وأيضا كنت أحد مهندسي الأقمار الصناعية،
I hadn't thought about using satellite imagery
لم يخطر لي بأن أستخدم صور الأقمار الصناعية
in my work.
في عملي.
Now, like most of us, I'd been online,
وكمعظمنا ،استخدمت الانترنت،
I'd see my house, so I thought,
لأرى منزلي ،لذا فكرت،
I'll hop in there and I'll start looking up
أن أتنقل ضمن الخريطة،وأبحث عن
some of these facilities.
بعض من تلك الوسائل.
And what I found really surprised me.
وما وجدته قد فاجأني حقا.
The pictures that I was finding
الصور التي رأيتها
were years out of date,
مأخوذة منذ سنوات ،
and because of that,
وبسبب ذلك،
it had relatively little relevance
كانت ذو أهمية ضئيلة
to the work that I was doing today.
للعمل الذي كنت أقوم به .
But I was intrigued.
ولكن كنت مفتون.
I mean, satellite imagery is pretty amazing stuff.
أعني بأن صور الأقمار الصناعية لشيء مذهل
There are millions and millions of sensors
اليوم ,هناك الملايين والملايين من أجهزة الاستشعار
surrounding us today,
المحيطة بنا ،
but there's still so much we don't know on a daily basis.
ولكن لا يزال هناك الكثير مما لا نعرفه في حياتنا اليومية.
How much oil is stored in all of China?
كم مقدار النفط المخزن في الصين؟
How much corn is being produced?
كم يُنتج من الذرة؟
How many ships are in all of our world's ports?
كم عدد السفن في جميع موانئ العالم؟
Now, in theory, all of these questions
، من الناحية النظرية، كل هذه الأسئلة
could be answered by imagery,
يمكن أن يجاب عنها بالصور،
but not if it's old.
لكن ليس إذا كانت قديمة
And if this data was so valuable,
و لا تحوي على بيانات ذات قيمة،
then how come I couldn't get my hands
فكيف لي أن أحصل على
on more recent pictures?
صور حديثة؟
So the story begins over 50 years ago
القصة تبدأ منذ أكثر من 50 عاما
with the launch of the first generation
مع إطلاق الجيل الأول
of U.S. government photo reconnaissance satellites.
من أقمار الاستطلاع للولايات المتحدة
And today, there's a handful
اليوم، لدينا القليل
of the great, great grandchildren
من هذه الآلات القديمة
of these early Cold War machines
تعود لأوائل الحرب الباردة
which are now operated by private companies
التي تديرها الآن شركات خاصة
and from which the vast majority of satellite imagery
والتي تأتي منها أغلب الصور
that you and I see on a daily basis comes.
التي نراها بشكل يومي.
During this period, launching things into space,
وخلال هذه الفترة،إطلاق هذه الأشياء للفضاء،
just the rocket to get the satellite up there,
تحتاج لتركيبها على صاروخ ووضعها في مدارها،
has cost hundreds of millions of dollars each,
و كل عملية كهذه تكلف ملايين الدولارت ،
and that's created tremendous pressure
وهذا ما يخلق ضعوط هائلة
to launch things infrequently
لإطلاقها بشكل غير منتظم
and to make sure that when you do,
وللتأكد من أنه عندما تقوم بذلك،
you cram as much functionality in there as possible.
تضع أكبر قدر ممكن من الوظائف .
All of this has only made satellites
جميع هذه الأمور جعلت من الأقمار الصناعية
bigger and bigger and bigger
أكبر وأكبر وأكبر
and more expensive,
وأكثر كلفة،
now nearly a billion, with a b, dollars per copy.
الآن حوالي 1 مليار دولار لكل واحد منها.
Because they are so expensive,
ولأنها مكلفة جداً،
there aren't very many of them.
لذلك لا يوجد الكثير منها.
Because there aren't very many of them,
ولأنه لايوجد الكثير منها،
the pictures that we see on a daily basis
فالصور التي نراها يوميا
tend to be old.
تكون قديمة.
I think a lot of people actually understand this anecdotally,
وأعتقد فعلا أن الكثير من الناس, يفهم هذه الحكاية،
but in order to visualize just how sparsely
ولكن من أجل تصور فقط أن القليل
our planet is collected,
يتم جمعه عن كوكبنا،
some friends and I put together a dataset
وضعت مع بعض الأصدقاء مجموعة من البيانات
of the 30 million pictures that have been gathered
تضم 30 مليون صورة تم جمعها
by these satellites between 2000 and 2010.
بهذه الأقمار الصناعية بين عامي 2000 و 2010.
As you can see in blue, huge areas of our world
كما يمكنك أن ترى في الأزرق ،مناطق كبيرة من عالمنا
are barely seen, less than once a year,
بالكاد تشاهد، مرة واحدة في العام،
and even the areas that are seen most frequently,
وحتى في المناطق التي تشاهد في أغلب الأحيان،
those in red, are seen at best once a quarter.
تلك التي باللون الأحمر، تصور في أفضل الأحوال مرة كل ربع عام.
Now as aerospace engineering grad students,
الآن كطلاب هندسة فضائية متخرجين،
this chart cried out to us as a challenge.
يقف هذا المخطط بالنسبة لنا كتحدي
Why do these things have to be so expensive?
لماذا هذه الأشياء يجب أن تكون مكلفة جداً؟
Does a single satellite really have to cost
هل حقاً قمر صناعي واحد كتكلفة
the equivalent of three 747 jumbo jets?
ما يعادل ثلاثة طائرات 747 الجامبو؟
Wasn't there a way to build a smaller,
ألم يكن هنالك من وسيلة لبناء أقمار صناعية جديدة أصغر حجماً،
simpler, new satellite design that could enable
وأكثر بساطة، والتي تسطيع
more timely imaging?
التقاط الصور بشكل أكثر؟
I realize that it does sound a little bit crazy
وأنا أدرك أن ذلك يبدو من جنون
that we were going to go out and just
نحن ذاهبون إلى الغير مألوف بقيامنا
begin designing satellites,
ببدء تصميم الأقمار الصناعية،
but fortunately we had help.
ولكن لحسن الحظ حصلنا على مساعدة.
In the late 1990s, a couple of professors
في أواخر التسعينات، واثنين من الأساتذة
proposed a concept for radically reducing the price
اقترحا مفهوم للتخفيض الجذري من السعر
of putting things in space.
لوضع الأشياء في الفضاء.
This was hitchhiking small satellites
وهذا كان إطلاق أقمار صناعية صغيرة
alongside much larger satellites.
بجانب الأقمار الصناعية الكبيرة
This dropped the cost of putting objects up there
وهذا يخفض من تكلفة وضع الأشياء في الفضاء
by over a factor of 100,
بـ 100 مرة أقل،
and suddenly we could afford to experiment,
وفجأة استطعنا تحمل هذه التجربة،
to take a little bit of risk,
لتأخذ القليل من الخطر،
and to realize a lot of innovation.
ولتحقيق الكثير من الابتكار.
And a new generation of engineers and scientists,
وجيل جديد من المهندسين والعلماء،
mostly out of universities,
معظمهم من الجامعات،
began launching these very small,
والبدء بإطلاق هذه الأشياء الصغيرةً،
breadbox-sized satellites called CubeSats.
أقمار صناعية بحجم صندوق الخبز تدعى "كب ساتس".
And these were built with electronics obtained
وصنعت من قطع إلكترونية تم الحصول عليها
from RadioShack instead of Lockheed Martin.
"من "راديو شاك" بدلاً من شركة" لوكهيد مارتن.
Now it was using the lessons learned from these early missions
و تم استخدام الدروس المستفادة من هذه البعثات في وقت مبكر
that my friends and I began a series of sketches
أنا وأصدقائي، بدأنا سلسلة من الرسومات
of our own satellite design.
لتصميم الأقمار الصناعية الخاصة بنا.
And I can't remember a specific day
ولا أتذكر يوم محدد
where we made a conscious decision
حيث اتخذنا قرارا واعيا
that we were actually going to go out and build these things,
نحن في الواقع ذاهبون بعيدا، لبناء مثل هذه الأشياء،
but once we got that idea in our minds
وحالما سيطرت هذه الفكرة في عقولنا
of the world as a dataset,
العالم كمجموعة من البيانات
of being able to capture millions of data points
والقدرة عل جمع الملايين من نقاط البيانات
on a daily basis describing the global economy,
تصف بشكل يومي الاقتصاد العالمي،
of being able to unearth billions of connections
للتمكن من كشف مليارات اتصالات
between them that had never before been found,
بينهم ، والتي لم تكن قد وجدت من قبل
it just seemed boring
سيبدو من الممل
to go work on anything else.
الانتقال على العمل على أي شيء آخر.
And so we moved into a cramped,
وهكذا انتقلنا إلى مكتب،
windowless office in Palo Alto,
مزدحم بدون نوافذ في بالو ألتو،
and began working to take our design
وبدأنا العمل على نقل تصميمنا
from the drawing board into the lab.
من لوحة الرسم إلى المخبر.
The first major question we had to tackle
المسألة الرئيسية الأولى هي التعامل
was just how big to build this thing.
مع ضخامة بناء مثل هذا الشيىء.
In space, size drives cost,
في الفضاء، الحجم يرفع التكلفة،
and we had worked with these very small,
و عملنا مع هذه الأقمار الصناعية الصغيرة ،
breadbox-sized satellites in school,
بحجم صندوق الخبز، في المدرسة،
but as we began to better understand the laws of physics,
ولكن عندما بدأنا فهم قوانين الفيزياء،
we found that the quality of pictures
وجدنا أن جودة الصور
those satellites could take was very limited,
التي تأخذها تلك الأقمار الصناعية كانت محدودة للغاية،
because the laws of physics dictate
لأن قوانين الفيزياء تشير
that the best picture you can take through a telescope
أن أفضل صورة يمكن أن تأخذها من خلال تلسكوب
is a function of the diameter of that telescope,
هي تابعة لقطر ذلك التلسكوب،
and these satellites had a very small,
وهذه الأقمار الصناعية كانت صغيرة جداً،
very constrained volume.
محدودة الحجم جداً.
And we found that the best picture we would
ووجدنا أنه أفضل صورة
have been able to get looked something like this.
يمكن الحصول عليها تبدو كهذه.
Although this was the low-cost option,
على الرغم من أن هذا كان خيار منخفض التكلفة،
quite frankly it was just too blurry
بصراحة كان واضح جداً
to see the things that make satellite imagery valuable.
لرؤية الأشياء التي تجعل الصور الأقمار الصناعية ذات قيمة.
So about three or four weeks later,
وبعد ثلاث أو أربع أسابيع ،
we met a group of engineers randomly
التقينا مجموعة من المهندسين مصادفة
who had worked on the first
والذين عملوا على تطوير أول
private imaging satellite ever developed,
قمر الصناعي خاص للتصوير ،
and they told us that back in the 1970s,
وأخبرونا أن ذلك يعود إلى السبعينيات،
the U.S. government had found a powerful
وقد وجدت حكومة الولايات المتحدة
optimal tradeoff --
مفاضلة فعّالة ومثلى
that in taking pictures at right about one meter resolution,
أنه في أخذ الصور بدقة واحد متر،
being able to see objects one meter in size,
ستتمكن من رؤية الأجسام في حجم واحد متر
they had found that they could not just get very high-quality images,
وقد وجدوا أنه ليس مجرد الحصول على صور ذات جودة عالية جداً فقط ،
but get a lot of them at an affordable price.
وإنما الحصول على الكثير منهم بسعر معقول.
From our own computer simulations,
من المحاكيات الحاسوبية الخاصة بنا،
we quickly found that one meter really was
وجدنا بسرعة أنه متر واحد كان حقاً
the minimum viable product
أدنى منتج قابل للتطبيق
to be able to see the drivers of our global economy,
لتكون قادراً على رؤية القوى المحركة للاقتصاد العالمي،
for the first time, being able to count
للمرة الأولى، تكون قادر على عد
the ships and cars and shipping containers and trucks
السفن والسيارات وحاويات الشحن والشاحنات
that move around our world on a daily basis,
والتي تتحرك في أنحاء كوكبنا بشكل يومي
while conveniently still not being able to see individuals.
في حين لا يزال من غير الملائم القدرة على رؤية الأفراد.
We had found our compromise.
وقد وجدنا الحل الوسط.
We would have to build something larger
أنه علينا أن نبني شيئا أكبر
than the original breadbox,
من صندوق الخبز الحقيقي،
now more like a mini-fridge,
بحجم الثلاجة الصغيرة،
but we still wouldn't have to build a pickup truck.
ولكن ليس بحجم شاحنة بيك آب.
So now we had our constraint.
وحتى الآن نحن مقيدون.
The laws of physics dictated
قوانين الفيزياء هي التي تملي
the absolute minimum-sized telescope that we could build.
حجم التلسكوب الأصغر الذي يمكن بناؤه.
What came next was making the rest of the satellite
و الأمر التالي كان بناء بقية القمر الصناعي
as small and as simple as possible,
،بأصغر و أبسط ما يمكن
basically a flying telescope with four walls
بشكل أساسي تلسكوب بأربع ألواح
and a set of electronics smaller than a phone book
ومجموعة إلكترونيات أصغر من دفتر هاتف
that used less power than a 100 watt lightbulb.
والتي تستهلك طاقة أقل من 100 واط كمصباح إنارة.
The big challenge became actually taking
وأصبح التحدي الكبير هو أخذ
the pictures through that telescope.
الصور عن طريق هذا التلسكوب.
Traditional imaging satellites use a line scanner,
أقمار التصوير التقليدية تستخدم ماسح خطي،
similar to a Xerox machine,
مماثلة لجهاز زيروكس،
and as they traverse the Earth, they take pictures,
وباجتيازها الأرض، تأخذ الصور،
scanning row by row by row
تمسح صفا بصف
to build the complete image.
لتكوين الصورة الكاملة.
Now people use these because they get a lot of light,
الأن تستخدم هذه التقنية لأنها تجمع الكثير من الضوء،
which means less of the noise you see
وهو ما يعني قدر أقل من التشويش لتراها
in a low-cost cell phone image.
في صورة منخفضة التكلفة لهاتف الخليوي.
The problem with them is they require
والمشكلة معها أنها تتطلب
very sophisticated pointing.
ضبط متطور جداً للتوضع.
You have to stay focused on a 50-centimeter target
عليك أن تبق التركيز على هدف 50 سنتيمتر
from over 600 miles away
من علو أكثر من 600 كم
while moving at more than seven kilometers a second,
بينما تتحرك بسرعة أكبر من سبعة كيلومترات في الثانية،
which requires an awesome degree of complexity.
الأمر الذي يتطلب درجة رهيبة من التعقيد.
So instead, we turned to a new generation of video sensors,
بدلاً من ذلك، نحن انتقلنا إلى جيل جديد من أجهزة الاستشعار، والفيديو
originally created for use in night vision goggles.
أنشئت أصلاً للاستخدام في النظارات الرؤية الليلية.
Instead of taking a single, high quality image,
بدلاً من تأخذ صورة واحدة عالية جودة،
we could take a videostream
يمكن أن تأخذ تسجيل فيديو
of individually noisier frames,
من الصور المفردة و الأكثر تشويش،
but then we could recombine
ولكن بعدها يمكنك إعادة تجميع
all of those frames together
كل تلك الصور معا
into very high-quality images
للحصول على صور ذات جودة عالية جداً
using sophisticated pixel processing techniques
باستخدام تقنيات معالجة متطورة للبكسل
here on the ground,
هنا على الأرض ،
at a cost of one one hundredth a traditional system.
بتكلفة قدرها واحد بمئة من النظام التقليدي.
And we applied this technique
وقمنا بتطبيق هذه التقنية
to many of the other systems on the satellite as well,
على العديد من النظم الأخرى على الأقمار الصناعية،،
and day by day, our design evolved
يوما بعد يوم،تصميمنا تطور
from CAD to prototypes
من التصميم الحاسوبي إلى النموذج الأولي
to production units.
إلى وحدات الإنتاج.
A few short weeks ago,
وقبل أسابيع قليلة
we packed up SkySat 1,
جهزنا سكاي سات 1
put our signatures on it,
وضعنا تواقيعنا عليه،
and waved goodbye for the last time on Earth.
ولوحنا له وداعا للمرة الأخيرة على الأرض.
Today, it's sitting in its final launch configuration
اليوم، هو ينتظر لتهيئة الانطلاق
ready to blast off in a few short weeks.
ويستعد للإطلاق في الأسابيع القليلة التالية.
And soon, we'll turn our attention to launching
وقريبا، سوف نوجه اهتمامنا إلى إطلاق
a constellation of 24 or more of these satellites
مجموعة من 24 أو أكثر من هذه الأقمار الصناعية
and beginning to build the scalable analytics
وبداية لتكوين تحليلات متغيرة الحجم
that will allow us to unearth the insights
والتي ستسمح لنا بكشف رؤى
in the petabytes of data we will collect.
بحجم بيتابايت من البيانات المجموعة
So why do all of this? Why build these satellites?
فلماذا نفعل كل هذا؟ لماذا نبني هذه الأقمار الصناعية؟
Well, it turns out imaging satellites
حسنا، كما تبين في تصوير الأقمار الصناعية
have a unique ability to provide global transparency,
ان لديها قدرة فريدة على توفير الشفافية العالمية،
and providing that transparency on a timely basis
وتوفير الشفافية في الوقت المناسب
is simply an idea whose time has come.
ببساطة هي فكرة قد حان وقتها .
We see ourselves as pioneers of a new frontier,
ونحن نرى أنفسنا كرواد لأفق جديد
and beyond economic data,
من البيانات الاقتصادية،
unlocking the human story, moment by moment.
نطلق الحكاية البشرية، لحظة بلحظة.
For a data scientist
بالنسبة لعالم البيانات
that just happened to go to space camp as a kid,
إن الذهاب إلى مخيم فضاء في الطفولة،
it just doesn't get much better than that.
ليس بالشيء الأحسن من هذا.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)